<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-24T15:39:23+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/2025-07-11-Online_latex_editor/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2025-12-24T15:39:23+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-24T15:39:23+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/2025-07-11-Online_latex_editor</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/2025-07-11-Online_latex_editor/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="online-latex-editors-and-collaboration-tools-for-academic-writing-features-pricing-and-security">Online LaTeX Editors and Collaboration Tools for Academic Writing: Features, Pricing, and Security</h1> <p><strong>Date:</strong> September 11, 2025</p> <h2 id="abstract">Abstract</h2> <p>This post provides a comprehensive analysis of online LaTeX editors and collaboration tools designed for academic writing. We examine leading platforms including Overleaf, Papeeria, Authorea, and other alternatives, comparing their features, pricing models, and collaborative capabilities. Special attention is given to available AI powered writing assistant and to data security and privacy compliance (particularly GDPR) for protecting sensitive academic content. Users should choose the solution that best fits requirements and budget constrains. Our analysis reveals that while in online LaTeX editors offer significant advantages for collaborative academic writing, institutions must carefully evaluate security implications when handling sensitive research data. Different set of features are offered across a tiered pricing model, ranging from robust free plans to professional tiers costing up to 40 €/month.</p> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>LaTeX has become the gold standard for academic and scientific document preparation, especially in fields requiring complex notation, precise formatting, and strong bibliographic management. The evolution from desktop to cloud-based collaborative platforms has revolutionized research workflows.</p> <p>Online LaTeX editors combine powerful typesetting with modern collaboration tools, enabling real-time editing, version control, and sharing across teams.</p> <h2 id="online-latex-editors">Online LaTeX Editors</h2> <p>The most popular and widely used online LaTeX editor is <em>Overleaf</em>, known for its collaborative features, real-time editing, document sharing, and extensive template library, making it a standard tool for academic and technical writing worldwide. Other popular online editors include <em>Papeeria</em> (https://papeeria.com) and <em>Authorea</em> (https://www.authorea.com). Beyond the most popular and established platforms, a new generation of online LaTeX editors is gaining traction. Also cloud-based managed computation platforms such as <em>CoCalc</em> (https://cocalc.com/) that include a LaTeX editor should be considered.</p> <h3 id="getting-started">Getting started</h3> <p>All online LaTeX featured a very friendly on-boarding process that allow the user to start writing in less than 2 minutes. Only an e-mail address is required activate a free plan instance. <em>CoCalc</em>, due to the different nature of the platform, require some more effort for the initial setup and do not provide a free plan.</p> <h3 id="overleaf">Overleaf</h3> <p>Overleaf is the dominant player, now serving over 17 million users. After merging with ShareLaTeX, it offers:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Real-time collaborative editing</p> </li> <li> <p>400+ academic templates</p> </li> <li> <p>Integrated PDF view and SyncTeX support</p> </li> <li> <p>Advanced bibliography management</p> </li> <li> <p>Git integration and document history</p> </li> <li> <p>Track changes and commenting system</p> </li> </ul> <p>Integration includes reference management tools (Zotero, Mendeley) and services like Dropbox and GitHub. Overleaf partners with Paperpal for grammar checking tailored to LaTeX documents.</p> <h3 id="papeeria">Papeeria</h3> <p>Papeeria emphasizes simplicity but retains robust LaTeX functionality. Unique features include:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Real-time collaboration</p> </li> <li> <p>Integrated plotting with gnuplot</p> </li> <li> <p>Version control and Git sync</p> </li> <li> <p>Auto-compiling on paid tiers</p> </li> <li> <p>Mendeley integration for references</p> </li> </ul> <p>Pricing: Free plan includes unlimited public projects, the Delta plan (USD 5/month) unlocks private projects and advanced features. Verified students get Delta features free.</p> <h3 id="authorea">Authorea</h3> <p>Authorea, acquired by Wiley, goes beyond LaTeX and supports:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Data integration (embedding datasets, plotting)</p> </li> <li> <p>Executable code blocks and Jupyter notebooks</p> </li> <li> <p>Journal-specific formatting for 40+ publishers</p> </li> <li> <p>Pre-print workflow integration</p> </li> </ul> <p>Best for computational research requiring close integration between text and data.</p> <h3 id="emerging-alternatives">Emerging Alternatives</h3> <h4 id="crixet">Crixet</h4> <p>Home site: https://crixet.com Crixet delivers a cross-browser, cross-device experience with LaTeX-aware intelligent autocompletion and inline error detection. Its standout feature, Chirp, functions as an AI co-pilot: users can type, speak, or even sketch ideas to generate LaTeX code, graphs, or tables seamlessly. Crixet also integrates fast citation search—tightly coupled with Zotero—and supports one-click refactoring of code into modular files. A forthcoming on-premise edition promises full feature parity with the cloud service, enabling organizations to host Crixet within their own infrastructure for maximum compliance and data control…. #### TeXPage</p> <p>Home site: https://www.texpage.com TeXPage focuses on simplicity and security with end-to-end encrypted transmission and encrypted at-rest storage, along with multiple redundant backups. Its real-time collaboration supports synchronous editing, asynchronous workflows, and rich commenting with track-change visibility. Beyond standard LaTeX editing, TeXPage offers a visual formula editor, auto-generating tables via an intuitive GUI, and a dynamic file outline panel for quick navigation. Version history is fully transparent, allowing users to restore earlier drafts at any time. TeXPage’s commitment to encrypted workflows makes it especially appealing for institutions with strict data-privacy mandates.</p> <h4 id="inscriveio">inscrive.io</h4> <p>Home site: https://inscrive.io Positioning itself as the only fully GDPR-compliant cloud LaTeX editor, inscrive.io emphasizes performance and unmetered compilation. Collaborators enjoy real-time editing with unlimited participants, backed by extensive version control and AI-accelerated compile speeds. By guaranteeing EU-based data processing and compliance with the latest privacy standards, inscrive.io offers peace of mind to European universities and research consortia. Its streamlined interface prioritizes fast loading times and minimal configuration, so users can focus on content creation without infrastructure concerns.</p> <h3 id="ai-support">AI Support</h3> <p>Modern online LaTeX platforms are increasingly embedding AI-powered assistants to streamline writing, debugging, and formatting workflows. By leveraging these AI assistants, researchers can focus more on substantive content and less on low-level formatting, making LaTeX more accessible to novices and veterans alike. Below are several concrete implementations.</p> <p><strong>Writefull</strong> (an add-on for Overleaf) offers AI-powered language assistance tailored for academic writing.</p> <h4 id="intelligent-autocompletion-and-error-detection">Intelligent Autocompletion and Error Detection</h4> <p>Crixet’s “Chirp” co-pilot (https://crixet.com/) uses AI to offer context-aware suggestions for macros, environments, and symbols, plus inline error detection that highlights compilation issues in real time.</p> <h4 id="natural-language-to-latex-conversion">Natural Language to LaTeX Conversion</h4> <p>Overleaf’s integration with Paperpal (https://paperpal.com/) lets users describe content in plain English—such as “a quadratic formula”—and receive fully formatted LaTeX code in seconds.</p> <h4 id="voice-and-sketch-driven-content-creation">Voice and Sketch-Driven Content Creation</h4> <p>Crixet (https://crixet.com/) allows voice dictation or freehand sketches to generate LaTeX code and vector graphics, accelerating drafts for users less familiar with raw syntax.</p> <h4 id="grammar-and-style-coaching">Grammar and Style Coaching</h4> <p>Writefull AI (https://writefull.com/) integrates directly into Overleaf, providing academic-style grammar checks, passive-voice alerts, and rephrasing suggestions that respect LaTeX document structure.</p> <h4 id="citation-and-bibliography-automation">Citation and Bibliography Automation</h4> <p>TeXPage (https://www.texpage.com/) features AI-driven citation lookup with one-click DOI metadata retrieval, seamless Zotero integration, and automatic bibliography formatting for both numbered and author–year styles.</p> <h4 id="collaborative-ai-driven-review">Collaborative AI-Driven Review</h4> <p>inscrive.io (https://inscrive.io/) employs AI to summarize recent edits, flag unresolved comments, and recommend missing citations or clarifications based on document content and version history.</p> <h2 id="feature-comparison">Feature Comparison</h2> <p>When selecting an online editor, you should consider your needs, requirements (such as security, privacy, data residency), budget constraints. The available solutions should be compared along the following dimensions:</p> <ol> <li> <p>Editing Capabilities and additional tools</p> </li> <li> <p>Collaboration</p> </li> <li> <p>Specific tools for academic writing (templates, journal submission automation)</p> </li> <li> <p>Simplicity</p> </li> <li> <p>Integration with external platform</p> </li> <li> <p>Cost and pricing plan available (including discounted offers for students or other categories)</p> </li> <li> <p>Resource limitations associated with the chosen plan such as compilation time, memory and storage limits</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="editing-capabilities">Editing Capabilities</h3> <p>All major platforms provide syntax highlighting, autocompletion, and error detection, but differ in specialist features:</p> <ol> <li> <p>Overleaf: Most comprehensive mathematical palette</p> </li> <li> <p>Papeeria: In-editor plotting tools</p> </li> <li> <p>Authorea: Executable content (notebooks)</p> </li> </ol> <h3 id="templates">Templates</h3> <p>Overleaf: 400+ templates spanning papers, dissertations, CVs; Papeeria: Focused, specialist templates; Authorea: Journal-specific.</p> <h3 id="collaboration-all-offer-simultaneous-multi-user-editing-overleaf-has-conflict-resolution-and-version-history-papeeria-offers-discussion-features-authorea-emphasizes-data-sharing">Collaboration… All offer simultaneous multi-user editing. Overleaf has conflict resolution and version history; Papeeria offers discussion features; Authorea emphasizes data-sharing.</h3> <h3 id="integration">Integration</h3> <p>Reference management (Zotero, Mendeley, Papers) and cloud sync (Dropbox, Google Drive, GitHub) vary by platform. The value of these features depend on your personal and team workflow.</p> <h2 id="pricing-comparison">Pricing Comparison</h2> <h3 id="overleaf-1">Overleaf</h3> <p>Free: Basic editing, 1 collaborator/project Standard ($199/year): 10 collaborators, history, advanced features Professional ($399/year): Unlimited collaborators, priority compile Institutional: Site-wide licenses with SSO, admin controls</p> <h3 id="papeeria-1">Papeeria</h3> <p>Delta plan: 5 USD /month, lower cost, most core features included</p> <p>Free premium for students</p> <h3 id="authorea-1">Authorea</h3> <p>Free for public docs; paid for private/research features</p> <h2 id="data-security-and-privacy">Data Security and Privacy</h2> <h3 id="gdpr-compliance">GDPR Compliance</h3> <p>EU institutions require platforms to meet GDPR for data processing, retention, deletion, and user control. Overleaf processes data in EU/US sites, is ISO/IEC 27001 certified, and meets data privacy framework requirements.</p> <h3 id="technical-safeguards">Technical Safeguards</h3> <p>All use HTTPS/TLS, encryption at rest, containerization, regular backups.</p> <h3 id="academic-risks">Academic Risks</h3> <p>Sensitive/unpublished content, patent material, or personal health data should be handled per institutional protocols. Platforms have had vulnerabilities in the past (e.g., ShareLaTeX command execution flaws), now mitigated with sandboxing and improved filtering.</p> <h3 id="security-best-practices">Security Best Practices</h3> <p>Institutions should:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Train users on sensitive content recognition</p> </li> <li> <p>Implement SSO/access controls</p> </li> <li> <p>Audit usage and backups</p> </li> <li> <p>Employ hybrid models for sensitive research</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="comparative-recommendations">Comparative Recommendations</h2> <p>Based on the present survey and 5 years of daily user experience my favorite tools is <em>Overleaf</em>, but it is also the most expensive. I found a better features versus cost balance in <em>TeXPage</em> and <em>www.papeeria.com</em> 5 € per month plans. My general advises are:</p> <ul> <li> <p>If your research institution provide institutional account probably you should take advantage of this benefit.</p> </li> <li> <p>Create a free account, import a project representative of you typical paper a try to work on the project for at lest few hours. Some days is better if possible.</p> </li> <li> <p>If you are a <em>privacy-focused</em> user (or you have to work under security constrains) consider on-premises solutions or at least an hybrid solution with most sensitive data keep in private server while using a public cloud based collaboration platform. EU based platform and data center may also help with security and privacy requirements.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="future-trends">Future Trends</h2> <p>AI integration (grammar, citation management, formula generation) are rising, with privacy risks to consider. End-to-end encryption, decentralized models, and zero-trust architectures are on the horizon.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Online LaTeX editors have radically improved academic writing workflows, with Overleaf leading in features and adoption. Data security and institutional policy remain central: hybrid approaches, regular audits, and robust training enable safe, productive research collaboration.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Dove pubblicare i tuoi tutorial e dispense di informatica</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/Dove_pubblicare_tutorial_e_dispense_informatica/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dove pubblicare i tuoi tutorial e dispense di informatica"/><published>2025-10-03T11:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-03T11:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/Dove_pubblicare_tutorial_e_dispense_informatica</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/Dove_pubblicare_tutorial_e_dispense_informatica/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="dove-pubblicare-i-tuoi-tutorial-e-dispense-di-informatica-quattro-piattaforme-per-citabilità-e-riconoscimento">Dove pubblicare i tuoi tutorial e dispense di informatica: quattro piattaforme per citabilità e riconoscimento</h1> <p>Hai scritto delle <strong>dispense</strong> dettagliate su machine learning, un <strong>tutorial</strong> su Python o una <strong>guida tecnica</strong> su Kubernetes? Ottimo!</p> <p>Prima di limitarti a un PDF sul tuo sito personale, a un post sul tuo blog o a un articolo su Medium, sappi che esistono piattaforme pensate per il mondo accademico e tecnico che ti permettono non solo di raggiungere una community mirata, ma anche di rendere il tuo lavoro permanentemente citabile da altri ricercatori e professionisti.</p> <p>Oltre a scrivere un post su Medium, è utile pubblicare il tuo lavoro su una piattaforma che garantisca la <strong>citabilità permanente</strong> (tramite DOI o ID persistente) e l’<strong>indicizzazione</strong> nei motori di ricerca accademici.</p> <p>Se pensi di pubblicare lo stesso materiale (o anche solo una parte di esso) su una rivista accademica, verifica prima la politica dell’editore (o della specifica rivista) sui cosiddetti <em>preprint</em>. Molte riviste accettano articoli che sono stati precedentemente pubblicati su preprint server riconosciuti, ma è sempre meglio controllare le regole specifiche della rivista.</p> <p>Di seguito trovi quattro ottime opzioni, classificate in base al loro focus disciplinare e alla tipologia di materiale che accettano.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="1-techrxiv-lautorità-tecnica-per-ingegneria-e-informatica-ieee">1. TechRxiv: l’autorità tecnica per ingegneria e informatica (IEEE)</h2> <p>Se le tue dispense riguardano il machine learning, la robotica o l’ingegneria elettrica, <strong>TechRxiv</strong> è una scelta mirata.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Cos’è:</strong> un server di preprint moderato, <strong>supportato dall’IEEE</strong> (Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers).</li> <li><strong>Visibilità &amp; indicizzazione:</strong> eccellente — è riconosciuto e indicizzato da <strong>Google Scholar</strong>, quindi il tuo lavoro sarà facilmente reperibile dalla comunità accademica di settore.</li> <li><strong>Citabilità:</strong> assegna un <strong>identificatore persistente</strong> che permette la citazione formale.</li> <li><strong>Ideale per:</strong> dispense di ML, report tecnici, guide avanzate su hardware o protocolli.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="2-arxiv-la-vetrina-della-ricerca-pura-massima-diffusione">2. arXiv: la vetrina della ricerca pura (massima diffusione)</h2> <p>Se le tue dispense sono strutturate come un <strong>survey</strong> o un <strong>report tecnico</strong> con l’obiettivo di raggiungere i ricercatori, prendi in considerazione <strong>arXiv</strong>.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Cos’è:</strong> il server di preprint originale e più grande, ampiamente usato nelle comunità di fisica, matematica e computer science (es. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">cs.LG</code> per machine learning).</li> <li><strong>Visibilità &amp; indicizzazione:</strong> massima — è lo standard de facto per la diffusione rapida della ricerca e gode di eccellente indicizzazione su Google Scholar.</li> <li><strong>Citabilità:</strong> utilizza un identificatore unico (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">arXiv:YYMM.#####</code>) universalmente riconosciuto.</li> <li><strong>Formato:</strong> il processo di submission richiede solitamente i sorgenti LaTeX.</li> <li><strong>Attenzione:</strong> arXiv è orientato alla ricerca originale; report e survey sono accettati se i moderatori li ritengono scientificamente rilevanti.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="3-zenodo-larchivio-flessibile-doi-e-archiviazione-multi-formato">3. Zenodo: l’archivio flessibile (DOI e archiviazione multi-formato)</h2> <p>Se cerchi la soluzione più semplice che garantisca un <strong>DOI</strong> e permetta di archiviare vari materiali, <strong>Zenodo</strong> è molto indicato.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Cos’è:</strong> un repository ad accesso aperto gestito dal <strong>CERN</strong>; accetta qualsiasi output della ricerca, inclusi report, software, dataset e materiale didattico.</li> <li><strong>Visibilità &amp; indicizzazione:</strong> buona — indicizzato da Google Search e Google Dataset Search; l’indicizzazione in Google Scholar non è automatica come per arXiv o TechRxiv, ma il DOI garantisce la citabilità.</li> <li><strong>Citabilità:</strong> assegna un <strong>DOI (Digital Object Identifier)</strong> a ogni pubblicazione.</li> <li><strong>Ideale per:</strong> dispense accompagnate da codice sorgente o dataset (tutto in un unico record DOI).</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="4-ssrn-la-rete-di-lavoro-accademico-focus-su-working-paper">4. SSRN: la rete di lavoro accademico (focus su working paper)</h2> <p>SSRN è un’opzione valida soprattutto se il tuo lavoro si colloca all’intersezione tra informatica e altre discipline come economia o diritto.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Cos’è:</strong> nato per le scienze sociali, oggi di proprietà di Elsevier, si è ampliato includendo anche ambiti di computer science e engineering; è focalizzato sui <strong>working paper</strong>.</li> <li><strong>Visibilità &amp; indicizzazione:</strong> molto buona — particolarmente diffuso negli Stati Uniti per la diffusione preliminare della ricerca.</li> <li><strong>Citabilità:</strong> fornisce un <strong>identificatore persistente</strong> ed è integrato con varie metriche accademiche.</li> <li><strong>Ideale per:</strong> documenti in stile “report accademico” o working paper, o lavori con forte intersezione con scienze sociali.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h3 id="quale-scegliere">Quale scegliere?</h3> <p>La scelta dipende dall’argomento, dallo scopo della pubblicazione e dal tipo di materiale (documento LaTeX, documento Word, file con dataset, codice sorgente, software associato, ecc.). Esempio per dispense di machine learning già pronte in LaTeX/PDF:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left">Scenario</th> <th style="text-align: left">Piattaforma raccomandata</th> <th style="text-align: left">Motivo principale</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Priorità: visibilità accademica e reputazione settoriale</strong></td> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>TechRxiv</strong></td> <td style="text-align: left">Supportato dall’IEEE, ottima indicizzazione in Google Scholar per il settore.</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Priorità: flessibilità, DOI standard, archivio dati/codice</strong></td> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Zenodo</strong></td> <td style="text-align: left">Semplice da usare e garantisce un DOI per ogni tipo di output.</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Priorità: massima diffusione nella ricerca pura</strong></td> <td style="text-align: left"><strong>arXiv</strong></td> <td style="text-align: left">Piattaforma leader per i preprint in computer science.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Scegliendo una di queste piattaforme, ti assicuri che le tue dispense non siano solo lette, ma diventino parte della letteratura citabile della comunità.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="preprint"/><category term="openaccess"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[piattaforma online dove pubblicare tutorial, dispense e risultati di ricerca]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with plotly.js</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with plotly.js"/><published>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/plotly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/plotly/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://plotly.com/javascript/">plotly</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "type": "scatter"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "type": "scatter"
    }
  ]
}
</code></pre> <p>Also another example chart.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">plotly
</span><span class="sb">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This is how it looks like:</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [10, 15, 13, 17],
      "mode": "markers"
    },
    {
      "x": [2, 3, 4, 5],
      "y": [16, 5, 11, 9],
      "mode": "lines"
    },
    {
      "x": [1, 2, 3, 4],
      "y": [12, 9, 15, 12],
      "mode": "lines+markers"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Line and Scatter Plot"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="charts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included plotly.js code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hosting a Personal Website on GitHub Pages</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/hosting-website-github/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hosting a Personal Website on GitHub Pages"/><published>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-26T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/hosting-website-github</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2025/hosting-website-github/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently decided it was time to refresh my personal website. Since I prefer to avoid dealing with virtual servers and hosting maintenance, GitHub Pages has become my go-to solution.</p> <p>Hosting a personal website on GitHub is a powerful way to establish a professional online presence with minimal cost and maintenance. In this post, I’ll walk you through the key concepts, benefits, and a practical workflow for getting started with GitHub Pages and a simple static site.</p> <h2 id="why-use-github-for-your-personal-website">Why Use GitHub for Your Personal Website</h2> <p>GitHub offers a feature called GitHub Pages, which can host static websites directly from a repository. This is ideal for personal portfolios, research pages, and blogs written in Markdown.</p> <p><strong>Key advantages include:</strong></p> <ul> <li><strong>Free</strong> hosting with automatic HTTPS and no bandwidth limits for typical personal use.</li> <li>Tight integration with Git: your site is version-controlled, reviewable, and easy to roll back.</li> <li>Native support for static site generators like Jekyll, making Markdown-based blogs and documentation straightforward to manage.</li> </ul> <h2 id="understanding-github-pages">Understanding GitHub Pages</h2> <p>GitHub Pages serves HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and other static assets from a special branch or repository. For a user site, the repository is typically named <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">username.github.io</code>, and GitHub automatically builds and publishes it.</p> <p><strong>Important characteristics:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Content is static: no server-side code such as Python, PHP, or Node.js runs on GitHub Pages.</li> <li>Sites can be either user/organization sites (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">username.github.io</code>) or project-specific sites under any repository.</li> <li>Configuration is managed via repository settings and simple configuration files, so most changes are handled through Git commits.</li> </ul> <h2 id="choosing-a-site-structure-and-workflow">Choosing a Site Structure and Workflow</h2> <p>Before writing content, decide how you want to manage your site:</p> <ul> <li>For a minimal portfolio, a hand-written HTML page plus a stylesheet may be enough.</li> <li>For content-heavy sites or blogs, using a static site generator like Jekyll simplifies layout reuse, navigation, and Markdown-based authoring.</li> <li>A hybrid approach often works well: a Jekyll site with separate sections for an “About” page, a research or projects portfolio, and a blog.</li> <li>A template-based website can offer more customization options.</li> </ul> <h3 id="1-simple-htmlcssjavascript">1. Simple HTML/CSS/JavaScript</h3> <ul> <li>Create a repository named <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">yourusername.github.io</code></li> <li>Add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">index.html</code>, CSS, and JS files</li> <li>Enable GitHub Pages in Settings</li> <li>Your site goes live at <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">https://yourusername.github.io</code></li> </ul> <h3 id="2-using-jekyll-githubs-built-in-generator">2. Using Jekyll (GitHub’s Built-in Generator)</h3> <ul> <li>Jekyll is automatically supported by GitHub Pages</li> <li>Supports Markdown-based blog posts and pages</li> <li>Choose from GitHub’s supported themes (Minima, Hacker, etc.)</li> <li>Ideal if you want blogging capabilities</li> </ul> <h3 id="3-using-pre-built-templates">3. Using Pre-built Templates</h3> <ul> <li>Clone a portfolio template repository (like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">al-folio</code> or others from GitHub Collections)</li> <li>Customize with your content</li> <li>Deploy with a single push</li> </ul> <h3 id="key-features-across-approaches">Key Features Across Approaches</h3> <ul> <li>✅ Free hosting</li> <li>✅ Free HTTPS</li> <li>✅ Custom domain support (optional)</li> <li>✅ No backend server needed (static sites only)</li> <li>✅ Built-in version control</li> <li>✅ Easy updates via Git</li> </ul> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="hosting"/><category term="hosting"/><category term="website"/><category term="github"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently decided to refresh my personal website. Since I prefer to avoid server and hosting maintenance, GitHub Pages is my go-to solution.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with image galleries</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with image galleries"/><published>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-04T01:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/photo-gallery/"><![CDATA[<p>The images in this post are all zoomable, arranged into different mini-galleries using different libraries.</p> <h2 id="lightbox2"><a href="https://lokeshdhakar.com/projects/lightbox2/">Lightbox2</a></h2> <p><a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-lightbox="roadtrip"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p> <hr/> <h2 id="photoswipe"><a href="https://photoswipe.com/">PhotoSwipe</a></h2> <div class="pswp-gallery pswp-gallery--single-column" id="gallery--getting-started"> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1669" data-pswp-height="2500" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="1875" data-pswp-height="2500" data-cropped="true" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/7/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <a href="https://unsplash.com" data-pswp-src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1666" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> <div> <a href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg" data-pswp-width="2500" data-pswp-height="1667" target="_blank"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg" alt=""/> </a> </div> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="spotlight-js"><a href="https://nextapps-de.github.io/spotlight/">Spotlight JS</a></h2> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <div class="spotlight-group"> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/4/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/5/img-200.jpg"/> </a> <a class="spotlight" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-2500.jpg"> <img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/6/img-200.jpg"/> </a> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="venobox"><a href="https://veno.es/venobox/">Venobox</a></h2> <p><a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/1/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/2/img-200.jpg"/></a> <a class="venobox" data-gall="myGallery" href="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-2500.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.photoswipe.com/photoswipe-demo-images/photos/3/img-200.jpg"/></a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="images"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included image galleries could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google Gemini updates: Flash 1.5, Gemma 2 and Project Astra"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/google-gemini-updates-flash-15-gemma-2-and-project-astra/"><![CDATA[<p>May 14, 2024 We’re introducing a series of updates across the Gemini family of models, including the new 1.5 Flash, our lightweight model for speed and efficiency, and Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants. In December, we launched our first natively multimodal model Gemini 1.0 in three sizes: Ultra, Pro and Nano. Just a few months later we released 1.5 Pro, with enhanced performance and a breakthrough long context window of 1 million tokens.Developers and enterprise customers have been putting 1.5 Pro to use in incredible ways and finding its long context window, multimodal reasoning capabilities and impressive overall performance incredibly useful.We know from user feedback that some applications need lower latency and a lower cost to serve. This inspired us to keep innovating, so today, we’re introducing Gemini 1.5 Flash: a model that’s lighter-weight than 1.5 Pro, and designed to be fast and efficient to serve at scale.Both 1.5 Pro and 1.5 Flash are available in public preview with a 1 million token context window in Google AI Studio and Vertex AI. And now, 1.5 Pro is also available with a 2 million token context window via waitlist to developers using the API and to Google Cloud customers.We’re also introducing updates across the Gemini family of models, announcing our next generation of open models, Gemma 2, and sharing progress on the future of AI assistants, with Project Astra.Context lengths of leading foundation models compared with Gemini 1.5’s 2 million token capability1.5 Flash is the newest addition to the Gemini model family and the fastest Gemini model served in the API. It’s optimized for high-volume, high-frequency tasks at scale, is more cost-efficient to serve and features our breakthrough long context window.While it’s a lighter weight model than 1.5 Pro, it’s highly capable of multimodal reasoning across vast amounts of information and delivers impressive quality for its size.The new Gemini 1.5 Flash model is optimized for speed and efficiency, is highly capable of multimodal reasoning and features our breakthrough long context window.1.5 Flash excels at summarization, chat applications, image and video captioning, data extraction from long documents and tables, and more. This is because it’s been trained by 1.5 Pro through a process called “distillation,” where the most essential knowledge and skills from a larger model are transferred to a smaller, more efficient model.Read more about 1.5 Flash in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report, on the Gemini technology page, and learn about 1.5 Flash’s availability and pricing.Over the last few months, we’ve significantly improved 1.5 Pro, our best model for general performance across a wide range of tasks.Beyond extending its context window to 2 million tokens, we’ve enhanced its code generation, logical reasoning and planning, multi-turn conversation, and audio and image understanding through data and algorithmic advances. We see strong improvements on public and internal benchmarks for each of these tasks.1.5 Pro can now follow increasingly complex and nuanced instructions, including ones that specify product-level behavior involving role, format and style. We’ve improved control over the model’s responses for specific use cases, like crafting the persona and response style of a chat agent or automating workflows through multiple function calls. And we’ve enabled users to steer model behavior by setting system instructions.We added audio understanding in the Gemini API and Google AI Studio, so 1.5 Pro can now reason across image and audio for videos uploaded in Google AI Studio. And we’re now integrating 1.5 Pro into Google products, including Gemini Advanced and in Workspace apps.Read more about 1.5 Pro in our updated Gemini 1.5 technical report and on the Gemini technology page.Gemini Nano is expanding beyond text-only inputs to include images as well. Starting with Pixel, applications using Gemini Nano with Multimodality will be able to understand the world the way people do — not just through text, but also through sight, sound and spoken language.Read more about Gemini 1.0 Nano on Android.Today, we’re also sharing a series of updates to Gemma, our family of open models built from the same research and technology used to create the Gemini models.We’re announcing Gemma 2, our next generation of open models for responsible AI innovation. Gemma 2 has a new architecture designed for breakthrough performance and efficiency, and will be available in new sizes.The Gemma family is also expanding with PaliGemma, our first vision-language model inspired by PaLI-3. And we’ve upgraded our Responsible Generative AI Toolkit with LLM Comparator for evaluating the quality of model responses.Read more on the Developer blog.As part of Google DeepMind’s mission to build AI responsibly to benefit humanity, we’ve always wanted to develop universal AI agents that can be helpful in everyday life. That’s why today, we’re sharing our progress in building the future of AI assistants with Project Astra (advanced seeing and talking responsive agent).To be truly useful, an agent needs to understand and respond to the complex and dynamic world just like people do — and take in and remember what it sees and hears to understand context and take action. It also needs to be proactive, teachable and personal, so users can talk to it naturally and without lag or delay.While we’ve made incredible progress developing AI systems that can understand multimodal information, getting response time down to something conversational is a difficult engineering challenge. Over the past few years, we’ve been working to improve how our models perceive, reason and converse to make the pace and quality of interaction feel more natural.Building on Gemini, we’ve developed prototype agents that can process information faster by continuously encoding video frames, combining the video and speech input into a timeline of events, and caching this information for efficient recall.By leveraging our leading speech models, we also enhanced how they sound, giving the agents a wider range of intonations. These agents can better understand the context they’re being used in, and respond quickly, in conversation.With technology like this, it’s easy to envision a future where people could have an expert AI assistant by their side, through a phone or glasses. And some of these capabilities are coming to Google products, like the Gemini app and web experience, later this year.We’ve made incredible progress so far with our family of Gemini models, and we’re always striving to advance the state-of-the-art even further. By investing in a relentless production line of innovation, we’re able to explore new ideas at the frontier, while also unlocking the possibility of new and exciting Gemini use cases.Learn more about Gemini and its capabilities. Your information will be used in accordance with Google’s privacy policy.</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>      Done. Just one step more.
    
      Check your inbox to confirm your subscription.
    You are already subscribed to our newsletter.
    You can also subscribe with a
    different email address
    
    .
    
  Let’s stay in touch. Get the latest news from Google in your inbox.
          Follow Us
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re sharing updates across our Gemini family of models and a glimpse of Project Astra, our vision for the future of AI assistants.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with tabs</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with tabs"/><published>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/tabs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/tabs/"><![CDATA[<p>This is how a post with <a href="https://github.com/Ovski4/jekyll-tabs">tabs</a> looks like. Note that the tabs could be used for different purposes, not only for code.</p> <h2 id="first-tabs">First tabs</h2> <p>To add tabs, use the following syntax:</p> <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tabs</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">tab-name-1</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

Content 1

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">tab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">group-name</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">tab-name-2</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

Content 2

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtab</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>

<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endtabs</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>With this you can generate visualizations like:</p> <ul id="log" class="tab" data-tab="f5b5283a-1f05-4fb1-94df-533527df7e8c" data-name="log"> <li class="active" id="log-php"> <a href="#">php </a> </li> <li id="log-js"> <a href="#">js </a> </li> <li id="log-ruby"> <a href="#">ruby </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="f5b5283a-1f05-4fb1-94df-533527df7e8c" data-name="log"> <li class="active"> <div class="language-php highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nb">var_dump</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'hello'</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nx">console</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">hello</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">);</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-javascript highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nx">pputs</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">hello</span><span class="dl">'</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> </ul> <h2 id="another-example">Another example</h2> <ul id="data-struct" class="tab" data-tab="b29b4de3-c4d1-437f-8f37-8bd81311978c" data-name="data-struct"> <li class="active" id="data-struct-yaml"> <a href="#">yaml </a> </li> <li id="data-struct-json"> <a href="#">json </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="b29b4de3-c4d1-437f-8f37-8bd81311978c" data-name="data-struct"> <li class="active"> <div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">hello</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">whatsup"</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="s">hi"</span>
</code></pre></div></div> </li> <li> <div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
  </span><span class="nl">"hello"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="s2">"whatsup"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"hi"</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div> </li> </ul> <h2 id="tabs-for-something-else">Tabs for something else</h2> <ul id="something-else" class="tab" data-tab="9bac0fdc-0702-44a8-957f-10a5565648a9" data-name="something-else"> <li class="active" id="something-else-text"> <a href="#">text </a> </li> <li id="something-else-quote"> <a href="#">quote </a> </li> <li id="something-else-list"> <a href="#">list </a> </li> </ul> <ul class="tab-content" id="9bac0fdc-0702-44a8-957f-10a5565648a9" data-name="something-else"> <li class="active"> <p>Regular text</p> </li> <li> <blockquote> <p>A quote</p> </blockquote> </li> <li> <p>Hipster list</p> <ul> <li>brunch</li> <li>fixie</li> <li>raybans</li> <li>messenger bag</li> </ul> </li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included tabs in a post could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with typograms</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with typograms"/><published>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-29T23:36:10+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/typograms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/typograms/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some <a href="https://github.com/google/typograms/">typograms</a> code.</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">+----+
|    |---&gt; My first diagram!
+----+
</code></pre> <p>Another example:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">typograms
</span><span class="sb">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>which generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-typograms">.------------------------.
|.----------------------.|
||"https://example.com" ||
|'----------------------'|
| ______________________ |
||                      ||
||   Welcome!           ||
||                      ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  | username       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |"*******"       |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
||  .----------------.  ||
||  |   "Sign-up"    |  ||
||  '----------------'  ||
||                      ||
|+----------------------+|
.------------------------.
</code></pre> <p>For more examples, check out the <a href="https://google.github.io/typograms/#examples">typograms documentation</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="diagrams"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included typograms code could look like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post that can be cited</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post that can be cited"/><published>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T15:06:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/post-citation/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post that can be cited. The content of the post ends here, while the citation information is automatically provided below. The only thing needed is for you to set the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">citation</code> key in the front matter to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="citation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what a post that can be cited looks like]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a post with pseudo code</title><link href="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a post with pseudo code"/><published>2024-04-15T00:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://emanubuc.github.io/blog/2024/pseudocode/"><![CDATA[<p>This is an example post with some pseudo code rendered by <a href="https://github.com/SaswatPadhi/pseudocode.js">pseudocode</a>. The example presented here is the same as the one in the <a href="https://saswat.padhi.me/pseudocode.js/">pseudocode.js</a> documentation, with only one simple but important change: everytime you would use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$</code>, you should use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">$$</code> instead. Also, note that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pseudocode</code> key in the front matter is set to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">true</code> to enable the rendering of pseudo code. As an example, using this code:</p> <div class="language-markdown highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">```</span><span class="nl">pseudocode
</span><span class="sb">% This quicksort algorithm is extracted from Chapter 7, Introduction to Algorithms (3rd edition)
\begin{algorithm}
\caption{Quicksort}
\begin{algorithmic}
\PROCEDURE{Quicksort}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \IF{$$p &lt; r$$}
        \STATE $$q = $$ \CALL{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, p, q - 1$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, q + 1, r$$}
    \ENDIF
\ENDPROCEDURE
\PROCEDURE{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \STATE $$x = A[r]$$
    \STATE $$i = p - 1$$
    \FOR{$$j = p$$ \TO $$r - 1$$}
        \IF{$$A[j] &lt; x$$}
            \STATE $$i = i + 1$$
            \STATE exchange
            $$A[i]$$ with $$A[j]$$
        \ENDIF
        \STATE exchange $$A[i]$$ with $$A[r]$$
    \ENDFOR
\ENDPROCEDURE
\end{algorithmic}
\end{algorithm}</span>
<span class="p">```</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Generates:</p> <pre><code class="language-pseudocode">% This quicksort algorithm is extracted from Chapter 7, Introduction to Algorithms (3rd edition)
\begin{algorithm}
\caption{Quicksort}
\begin{algorithmic}
\PROCEDURE{Quicksort}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \IF{$$p &lt; r$$}
        \STATE $$q = $$ \CALL{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, p, q - 1$$}
        \STATE \CALL{Quicksort}{$$A, q + 1, r$$}
    \ENDIF
\ENDPROCEDURE
\PROCEDURE{Partition}{$$A, p, r$$}
    \STATE $$x = A[r]$$
    \STATE $$i = p - 1$$
    \FOR{$$j = p$$ \TO $$r - 1$$}
        \IF{$$A[j] &lt; x$$}
            \STATE $$i = i + 1$$
            \STATE exchange
            $$A[i]$$ with $$A[j]$$
        \ENDIF
        \STATE exchange $$A[i]$$ with $$A[r]$$
    \ENDFOR
\ENDPROCEDURE
\end{algorithmic}
\end{algorithm}
</code></pre>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this is what included pseudo code could look like]]></summary></entry></feed>